Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov.
Today's דף daf is מ"ב mem bet officially, but we are wrapping
up, so we're in the bottom of מ"א עמוד א', mem aleph
amud aleph, we're on the top of מ"א עמוד ב', mem aleph
amud bet, and we are dealing with the debate of, or it's
the bottom of מ"ב עמוד א', mem bet amud aleph, מ"א עמוד
א'. mem aleph amud aleph. We're dealing with the debate of whether
half קנס knas by a goring ox, top of מ"א עמוד ב'.
mem aleph amud bet. Half payment of a goring ox is considered
קנס knas or ממון. mammon. The biggest difference is if somebody admits
it, do they have to pay or not? The משנה mishnah says
only if you pay more than the normal damages can we assume
a קנס, knas, lest it might be partial payment. But nevertheless, we
see that there's a debate of אמוראים amoraim about this in terms
of whether we can assume that oxen are normally considered to be
watched and guarded like naturally without doing anything, and therefore when it
goes out and gores and it's a תם, tam, it's actually falls
shy of being actual negligence and therefore would be a קנס, knas,
or is it actually just over the line of being negligent and
it would be ממון, mammon, but because it's just barely, it's half
payment. So now the גמרא gemara picks up on the top of
מ"א עמוד ב', mem aleph amud bet, and let's just try to
quickly wrap this up. תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear. המיש
שורו את פלוני, hamish shoro es ploni, second line of מ"א עמוד
ב'. mem aleph amud bet. המיש שורו את פלוני או שורו של
פלוני הרי זה משלם על פי עצמו. hamish shoro es ploni o
shoro shel ploni harei zeh meshalem al pi atzmo. So if somebody
says my ox gored a person, and as we discussed, that would
be a payment of the actual כופר, kofer, the monetary value of
the person himself, which is being assumed here as a type of
תשלומין, tashlumin, we're not going to focus on that, or it's the
person's ox, then he pays by his own admission. מאי לאו בתם,
mai lav b'tam, are we not talking about an unhabituated ox and
therefore he's paying by his own admission? It shows that it's ממון.
mammon. And the גמרא gemara says לא במועד, lo b'muad, no, we're
talking about habituated. The גמרא gemara says אבל בתם מאי, aval b'tam
mai, so what would you say therefore if it was a case
of a תם? tam? אינו משלם על פי עצמו, eino meshalem al
pi atzmo, you would say he would not pay based on his
own admission because then you would claim it would be a קנס.
knas. דתני סיפא, d'tani seifa, so if the end of the ברייתא
braita says עבדו של פלוני אינו משלם על פי עצמו, avdo shel
ploni eino meshalem al pi atzmo, that when you admit to your
ox goring somebody's slave you don't pay by your own admission because
a slave is thirty שקל, shekel, it's a fixed amount, it's a
קנס, knas, right? So the ברייתא braita there is contrasting the goring
of a free person where it's תשלומין tashlumin as opposed to a
slave where it's קנס. knas. So why did it have to jump
to a slave case? ונפלוג וניתני בדידיה, v'niflog v'nisnei b'didi, why don't
you make a distinction within the case itself? במה דברים אמורים, bameh
devarim amurim, when is it when you don't pay by your own
admission? I mean, that you do pay by your own admission, when
it's מועד, muad, habituated. אבל תם אינו משלם על פי עצמו, aval
tam eino meshalem al pi atzmo, but if it's an unhabituated, if
it's a תם, tam, you don't pay on your own admission, even
if it's a case of goring another ox or goring a free
person. Right? The fact that you had to run to the case
of slave seems to indicate that in a normal case you would
always pay even if it was a case of a תם. tam.
So the גמרא gemara says, so that seems to indicate that even
a תם tam is considered תשלומין. tashlumin. כולה במועד קאמרי, kula b'muad
ka'mari,
no, that doesn't prove anything. Maybe we don't want to be talking
about a תם. tam. Maybe we want to be talking about a
habituated ox and say even within a habituated ox there's differences. Goring
an ox and goring a free person is תשלומין, tashlumin, goring a
slave is a קנס. knas. But you know what? It's true, there's
other cases like an unhabituated ox, a תם, tam, that also would
be a קנס. knas. So the fact that we jumped to the
case of slave doesn't show anything about whether we feel whether תם
tam itself is תשלומין tashlumin or not. Okay. תא שמע, ta shma,
come and hear, going to our משנה. mishnah. זה הכלל, zeh haklal,
this is the rule. כל המשלם יתר על מה שהזיק אינו משלם
על פי עצמו. kol hameshalem yaser al mah she'hizik eino meshalem al
pi atzmo. Anytime you pay more than damages, you don't pay based
on your own admission, that's clearly a קנס, knas, a fine, because
it's exceeding the damages, or it's thirty of an עבד eved which
at times could exceed the damages, shows that it's a fine. So
the גמרא gemara says אינו משלם על פי עצמו. eino meshalem al
pi atzmo. הפחות ממה שהזיק, hapachus mimah she'hizik,
if you pay less than damages, than full damages, משלם על פי
עצמו, meshalem al pi atzmo, presumably you would pay based on your
own admission. If you're always paying half, then we shouldn't consider that
a fine, we should consider that partial payment,
and therefore you pay based on your own admission.
Doesn't that seem to be indicated in our משנה? mishnah? הגמרא gemara
says
לא, לא תימא הפחות ממה
שהזיק,
lo, lo teima
hapachus mimah she'hizik, don't say less than the full amount is would
be תשלומין. tashlumin. אלא אימא הכמא שהזיק משלם על פי עצמו, ella
eima hak'ma she'hizik meshalem al pi atzmo,
when it's exactly the full amount, that's when it's תשלומין. tashlumin. But
anything more is קנס, knas, and maybe anything less is also קנס.
knas. But when it's exactly the same amount as damages, that's when
it's תשלומין. tashlumin. So the גמרא gemara says, אבל פחות מאי, aval
pachus mai,
so one minute, the גמרא gemara is saying, you're saying that according
to the משנה mishnah not only is more קנס, knas, but even
less is a קנס. knas. So אבל פחות מאי, aval pachus mai,
אינו משלם על פי עצמו, eino meshalem al pi atzmo, so if
it's less you also don't pay? ליתני זה הכלל כל שאינו משלם
כמה שהזיק אינו משלם על פי עצמו. litni zeh haklal kol she'eino
meshalem k'ma she'hizik eino meshalem al pi atzmo.
Then the משנה mishnah should have been more precise. The משנה mishnah
should have said whenever you don't pay exactly according to damages, then
you don't
pay. The משנה Mishna says if you pay more than full damages
or potentially more like the 30 of an עבד, eved, it's a
קנס. knas. So the strong implication is less is not a קנס,
knas, less is partial payment. And if you wanted to say the
משנה Mishna really meant whether more or less, then say that. Say
if it's exactly the damages then it's תשלומין tashlumim and anything more
and anything less is a קנס. knas. It doesn't say that. It
says if it's more it's a קנס, knas, which means less is
not a קנס. knas. So the גמרא Gemara says תיופתא, Tshyufta, you
know what? You're right, that is a contradiction to the idea of
the one that says that it's a קנס. knas. The משנה Mishna
very strongly suggests that unless it's more than damages it's going to
be a fine. Anything less will also be considered תשלומין. tashlumim. So
the גמרא Gemara says so you're right, that contradicts the idea that
half payment is a קנס, knas, seems to very explicitly indicate that
half payment is תשלומין. tashlumim. So the גמרא Gemara says and but
just to make things fun והלכתא, v'hilchasa, but the ruling is פלגא
ניזקא קנסא, palga nizka knasa, that half of the half damages is
a קנס. knas.
So the משנה Mishna makes it almost explicit that it's תשלומין tashlumim
and we rule that it's a קנס. knas. So the גמרא Gemara
says תיופתא והלכתא? Tshyufta v'hilchasa?
What? You contradict it and then you rule that way? It says
אין, in, yes. טעמא מאי אותיבת? Ta'ama mai osivta? Why was the
position of half damages as a קנס knas contradicted? משום דלא קתני
כמו שהזיק, mishum d'lo kasni kemo shehizik, because it didn't say תשלומין
tashlumim is exactly the same amount, it said you know it said
anything more, not anything different than the exact. So that indicated that
something less would be תשלומין. tashlumim. Okay, that was your contradiction. I'll
give you a reason why it didn't say that. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא פסיקא ליה, lo psika lei, because it was not
absolute, it was not categorical that the real rule is that less
is also a קנס. knas. But there's one exception to the rule
so we couldn't exactly say it. What was the exception to the
rule? כיון דאיכא חצי נזק צרורות דהלכתא גמירי לה, keivan d'ika chatzi
nezek tzoros d'hilchasa gemiri lah, that there's half damages which is paid
by pebbles.
What does that mean? It means that if an ox is walking
and tramples on vessels as it's walking that's the נזק nezek of
רגל, regel, it pays full damages. If it's walking and it kicks
up stones and the stones breaks things then it pays half damages.
And that is a הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha l'Moshe MiSinai. And there
we the there's no question that that's considered רגל regel and that
actually it is well I first mean רגל, regel, it's a form
of תשלומי רגל tashlumei regel and that it pays half and that
it's תשלומין. tashlumim. And that therefore the half damages there is תשלומין.
tashlumim. So the גמרא Gemara says really our משנה Mishna did not
say that if it's not exact it's a קנס knas because there
is a case that's not exact that's less that's ממון mamon which
is this case of צרורות. tzoros. But the real rule is bracketing
the exception of צרורות, tzoros, anything that's not exactly the תשלומין, tashlumim,
whether it's more or whether it's less is going to be a
קנס. knas. And half payment of a תם tam of a goring
ox is actually going to be a קנס. knas. דהלכתא גמירי דממונא
הוא משום הכי לא קתני. Dehilchasa gemiri d'mamon hu mishum hachi lo
kasni. Okay, so that is
the גמרא's Gemara conclusion. The גמרא Gemara the pretty much the only
two that it's always exact it's always less, otherwise it's more or
שלושים של עבד shloshim shel eved which sometimes is more sometimes is
less.
Even though the thrust was that it was ממון, mamon, I do
understand, despite that we rule it was a קנס. knas.
Right, so that is correct, meaning all of the evidence seems to
point to the idea that פלגא ניזקא palga nizka that half damages
is ממון, mamon, right? All of the evidence we brought yesterday and
the wrap up of the סוגיא sugya today. And nevertheless, the גמרא
Gemara concludes that and logically if you're paying half of something, the
logic is is that that is partial payment not that it's you
should be paying zero but it's a fine. The logic is that
it's partial payment. And that's what we say by the צרורות tzoros
case by the pebbles being kicked by the walking animal. Nevertheless, we
conclude that this is a קנס. knas. I don't know, the גמרא
Gemara had a tradition that this was the that this was the
הלכה, halacha, that this was a קנס. knas. And therefore maybe it's
just decided that you know that a תם tam logically there's no
negligence, so it logically should be a קנס. knas. What negligence is
there that an ox would go out and gore? So therefore that's
the גמרא's Gemara conclusion and even though the משנה Mishna makes it
sound that in order to be a קנס knas it has to
be beyond damages, more than damages, right? But nevertheless it's saying no
there are times when even it's less than damages it's also a
קנס. knas. Okay, sometimes yes, sometimes no. Half damages by a goring
ox that would be a קנס. knas. Half damages by the pebbles
that would be תשלומין, tashlumim, yes.
What's the conceptual relationship between על פי עצמו al pi atzmo and
תשלומין? tashlumim?
That anytime we consider to be תשלומין ממון tashlumim mamon then you
pay based on על פי עצמו, al pi atzmo, they go together.
Whereas if it's Why do they go together?
Because you're always believed to obligate yourself in court to say that
you owe somebody money. The only point is that when it's קנס,
knas, when it's seen as a monetary fine imposed by בית דין,
Beis Din, then the same way בית דין Beis Din won't impose
lashes on you based on your own admission, we need objective testimony,
they won't impose monetary, the same way they won't impose bodily punishments
on you based on your own admission, they won't impose monetary punishments
based on your own admission. needs objective testimony, but admission to a
debt you can be done is על פי עצמו, al pi atzmo,
yeah.
So, the גמרא Gemara just eventually got back to the משנה Mishnah
which is the case we're in front of us, it dealt with
everything else until it got there, ignoring the most obvious proof. Is
that typical, what we did?
I don't know, it's a good question. Maybe we waited for it
to last. Maybe this סוגיא sugya was not originally on the משנה
Mishnah because the סוגיא sugya might have been originally in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma and then just pasted on here to the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay.
Wait, so is a קנס knas always, בית דין beis din is
not, it's not דאורייתא? d'Oraita?
No no no, קנס knas is imposed,
for example, the idea that you pay double in case of גניבה
gneivah or four and five is in the Torah. But the, but
the same way lashes are in the Torah. But if I go
ahead, if I say, if I owe you $100, with or without
בית דין beis din I pay you up. That exists, and if
I pay you up I've exempted myself from that debt, I've discharged
that debt. If I go ahead and I transgress a negative prohibition,
it's not like objectively I deserve lashes and if I go ahead
and impose self-imposed lashes now I've gotten out of my obligation, right?
The idea that the transgression empowers בית דין beis din to therefore
rule that I am obligated in lashes and impose those lashes. It
doesn't exist independent of the court. But בית דין beis din is
directed by the Torah to rule and impose lashes. And the same
would be by the קנס. knas. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues and it says the following. והשתא דאמרת פלגא ניזקא קנסא. Vehashta
de'amarta palga nizka knasa.
Now that you said that half damages is a קנס knas when
it's a case of a קרן keren and of a goring ox,
which means normally a קרן keren is understood to be an animal
that intentionally damages, okay, but now what we're going to do is
we're going to list cases where an animal does damage which is
משונה, meshuneh, unusual and unexpected and something you wouldn't guard against. And
there's an interesting question whether what the גמרא Gemara is doing is
it's saying that anytime it's unusual, that's put it in the category
of קרן? keren? Because normally we assume קרן keren means an animal
that's willfully damaging, okay,
but here the גמרא's Gemara going to deal with cases of משונה.
meshuneh. So one way of understanding is that it's categorizing it as
קרן. keren. The other way is no. Well let's take a look
at the cases. Okay. האי כלבא, Hai kalba, so if a certain
dog דאכל אימרי de'achal imrei that eats lambs, ושונרא veshunra or a
cat דאכל תרנגולי de'achal tarnegolei that eats chickens,
רברבי ravravi if they're large lambs or chickens, משונה הוא, meshuneh hu,
then it's an unusual act, ולא מגבינן בבבל velo magbinan be-Vavel and
therefore it would be a קנס knas and would only be half
damages, and another application of קנס knas is not only that you
don't pay based on your own admission, but as we were talking
about before it requires a court to impose it. And not only
any court, but the same way only a court that has סמיכה
smicha going back to משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu is called אלוהים Elohim
has that original סמיכה, smicha, since only that type of a court
can impose lashes, also you need that type of a court to
impose a monetary קנס. knas. And therefore it cannot be done outside
of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. It was assumed that those courts are
only empowered in Israel. They only have סמיכה, smicha, סמיכה smicha is
given in Israel, that type of סמיכה, smicha, and those courts are
empowered in Israel. So therefore you cannot collect things that are קנס,
knas, not only based on your own admission, you can't collect them
without the right court and you can't impose them outside of ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now the question is why is something משונה meshuneh
considered to be קרן? keren? קרן keren is a goring intentional animal,
here is an animal that's trying to eat a chicken or trying
to eat a lamb. What makes it a קרן? keren? It should
be like a שן, shein, an animal that does something as an
act of eating is in a different category. So basically there's a
lot of fun discussion in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. There are two
approaches. One approach is that this is the חידוש, chiddush, since it's
not a normal type of eating, it gets categorized as קרן keren
in the same category as intentional damage. The other approach is no,
maybe it is a שן. shein. But the same way by a
goring animal when it gores in a way that you should not
you could not have protected against, that you were not negligent for,
like the first few times you only pay half damages, so maybe
when an animal does a type of an eating that you couldn't
have protected against, an eating that was totally unexpected and that was
a תם tam for, maybe also you only pay half damages and
it's also a type of a קנס. knas. And then there becomes
this interesting idea of half damages not only for קרן keren but
even for something like שן shein and רגל. regel. So that's an
interesting discussion in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. But for us what we
have to know is that if it's this unusual type of thing,
it similarly would be half damages and similarly would be a קנס.
knas. ולא מגבינן בבבל. Velo magbinan be-Vavel. אבל זוטרי, Aval zutrei, if
it eats the small animals, אורחיה הוא, orcheih hu, that's normal, ומגבינן
umagbinan and we collect. ואי תפס לא מפקינן מיניה, Ve-i tphas la
mapkinan mineih, and even if we won't as a court rule that
the guy has to pay, if the damagee grabs money equivalent to
the injury or to half the cost of the injury from the
damager, then we will not force him to give the property back.
Of course the funny thing is then we'll have to have a
court case to decide how much the damages were and whether he's
entitled to keep as much as he grabbed. Anyway, ואי אמר אקבעו
לי זימנא לארץ ישראל, Ve-i amar akbe'u li zimna l'Eretz Yisrael, and
if he says though, if the damagee says to our בית דין,
beis din, make let's I want to set up a court case
in Israel and have the damager come to me to ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael so... to collect my due, מקבנינן ליה, makbinan leih, then
we do make a set an appointment for him as a בית
דין Beis Din in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that the damagee can
take the damager to. ואי לא אזיל, ve'ilo azil, and if the
damager won't go, משמתינן ליה, meshamtinan leih, we put him in חרם
cherem in order until he goes so therefore the guy the damagee
is not completely without recourse. בין כך ובין כך, bein kach uvein
kach, and whether or not he sets up a time the damagee
to go to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, either way משמתינן ליה meshamtinan
leih we will put the damager in חרם cherem until he takes
care of his dangerous animal, דאמרינן ליה סליק היזיקך. de'amrinan leih silik
hezeikach. We say remove your you know your dangerous animal.
And that's actually מדרבי נתן. mi-de-Rabbi Nosson.
Well, that's an interesting point. You're right. You could have said it's
a תם tam and maybe we would see it as a as
a like as an exception, right, as a as a freak incident.
But it's interesting, we don't. I mean you and that's an excellent
point. דתניא רבי נתן אומר, detanya Rabbi Nosson omer, Rabbi Nosson says
מנין שלא יגדל אדם כלב רע בתוך ביתו, minayin shelo yigdal adam
kelev ra besoch beiso, how do you know a person shouldn't raise
a mad dog in his house, ולא יעמיד סולם רעוע בתוך ביתו
velo ya'amid sulam ra'ua besoch beiso or have a shaky ladder, שנאמר
ולא תשים דמים בביתך. shene'emar velo sasim damim beveisecha. So Michael makes
a good point, like do we always do this or only if
the animal is starting to become more habitual or we have concerns
that this is not even if it's the first time it won't
be the last time. Anyway, not clear. הדרן עלך אלו נערות. hadran
alach eilu naaros. So that was wrapping up from yesterday, a very
nice sort of digression into בבא קמא Bava Kamma land about when
do we consider something to be ממון mamon and קנס, knas, whether
when it gets to be the fifty שקל shekel is always קנס
knas because that's seen as going beyond any damages and it's a
fixed amount. But something that is not a fixed amount that is
חצי נזק chatzi nezek half damages, that was an interesting discussion. We
would naturally consider that to be partial תשלומין. tashlumin. The גמרא Gemara
said at least in some cases like by the goring animal that
would be a קנס. knas. But a fixed amount and something that
could be more than damages is always going to be קנס knas
with two הלכות halachos so far, one is you don't pay based
on your own admission and the other is as we've seen that
you need a court to impose it and only a court with
סמיכה smicha and so on. Now we continue getting back to the
fifty of the case of rape and seduction and also to an
implication of its special status as a קנס. knas. So let's take
a look now as we move into the fourth פרק. perek. נערה
שנתפתתה, naara shenispateta, a woman that was seduced. Actually, now we're going
into seduction and not rape. בושת ופגם וקנסה של אביה. boshes upgam
uknasa shel aviha. So the בושת boshes and פגם, pgam, the right,
the shame and the injury and the fine, the fifty שקל shekel
goes to the father, okay? And again, even though she is consensual,
she's not in her own rights to be consensual about it and
therefore there still is injury and it goes to the father. והצער
vehatza'ar and additionally the pain and suffering בתפוסה bisphusa in a case
of rape. So here's a new word for rape, not אנוסה anusa
but תפוסה tfusa because the תורה Torah says והיא לא נתפשה, vehi
lo nitpasha, she was not grabbed. So to be נתפסה, nitpasa, to
be forcibly seized is the language in the גמרא Gemara in the
תורה Torah by rape. So in a case of rape, there's also
צער tza'ar and that also goes to the father. So that's repeating
the idea that all the payments go to the father. Now we're
going to look at exceptions to that case. עמדה בדין. amda bedin.
But didn't we say there
was no צער tza'ar earlier?
except for rape. That's what it says, וצער בתפוסה vehatza'ar bisphusa and
there's צער tza'ar payment in a case of rape. עמדה בדין, amda
bedin, now let's say we have the court case, okay, and the
it was brought to the court and the בית דין Beis Din
said to the guy חייב אתה ליתן לו, chayav ata liten lo,
you have to pay the father. Now עד שלא מת האב ad
shelo mes ha'av and the father is alive at the time of
the court
case,
and then they ruled that you that the guy has to pay.
They had the court case, the father was alive, they ruled that
the guy had to pay the father. Fine, הרי הן של אב,
harei hen shel av, then the father already is entitled to the
money because he was around when the when the ruling occurred in
בית דין. Beis Din. מת האב, mes ha'av, now let's say the
father dies after the court case. So the father already was awarded
the funds, so even if he didn't pocket it yet, הרי הן
של אחין, harei hen shel achin, then that passes on to his
sons, the the brothers of the woman who was raped, okay, because
he was entitled to that. It's like a guy now owes him
a hundred dollars, he dies, so that debt transfers to his heirs.
הרי הן של אחין. harei hen shel achin. לא הספיקה לעמוד בדין
עד שמת האב. lo hispika la'amod bedin ad shemes ha'av. Let's say
that you did not yet have the court case and the father
had died. The father died before the rapist was taken to court.
Okay, so now הרי הן של עצמה. harei hen shel atzma. Now
it's when we have the court case, she is the litigant and
and it is awarded to her, okay.
So this gets back to the idea...
No meaning regardless of when she's a בוגרת bogeres or not?
Yeah, correct, because the basic idea is as we've said or this
is conceptually the easiest way to explain it, that the guy did
this act of injury and rape to this woman, he owes the
money to the woman, but the father's entitled as it through his
daughter, that he's entitled to anything that money would go to his
daughter. If he's dead when the time of the court case comes,
then she's been emancipated from the father. So now she can collect
it directly and therefore if the father's dead and they have the
court case, she's the one that gets the money. Okay, הרי הן
של עצמה. harei hen shel atzma. עמדה בדין עד שלא בגרה. amda
bedin ad shelo bagra. Now let's say
she
has the court case and she is still a קטנה. ktana. הרי
הן של אב. Harei hen shel av. Then they then they then
they go to the father. That's again assuming that the father's alive,
so this is just going back to our case, but we're now
going to be dealing with the question of her age. So the
father's alive and she's a קטנה, ktana, then the father gets it.
Why קטנה? ktana? Maybe a נערה. na'ara. נערה, na'ara, fine.
מת האב הרי הן של אחין, Met ha'av harei hen shel achin,
then the father dies after he's been awarded the money, it goes
to the brothers. Okay, so fine. That was basically reviewing the other
case except just pointing out that in the case that the father
gets it, not only is the father alive but she's also not
a בוגרת. bogeret. But in the two exceptions to that, one is
that the father is dead, or exception number two, at the time
of the court case she's a בוגרת. bogeret. לא הספיק לעמוד בדין
עד שבגרה, Lo hispik la'amod badin ad shebagra, or she's a בוגרת,
bogeret, she is now a full adult and fully emancipated at the
time of the court case, then הרי הן של עצמה, Harei hen
shel atzma, they're hers. Okay? So bottom line the Mishnah is saying
when does the father get it through her? In order for him
to get it, he has to be alive and she has to
be a נערה na'ara or קטנה ktana at the time of the
court case. If she is emancipated what? At the fine at the
ending of the case. If she's emancipated when the case is over,
when it gets awarded, she is either the father has died or
she's a בוגרת, bogeret, then the money gets awarded to her and
not to the father. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, and Rabbi
Shimon says: אם לא הספיק לגבות עד שמת האב הרי הן של
עצמה. Im lo hispik ligbot ad shemet ha'av harei hen shel atzma.
No, it's not enough that actually for the father to be awarded
it, it's not enough that there's the גמר דין. gmar din. For
it to actually be considered the father's, actually the money has to
be paid out already, it has to be in the father's pocket.
But if basically even after the court case the father before the
money was paid out, the father died, then it's still going to
be paid to her, not to the father. So according to Rabbi
Shimon, even after גמר דין, gmar din, the obligation is still not
directly to the father, but it's to the father through the daughter.
You get it? So the case has come to court and the
guy says, "Okay Reuven, you seduced Shimon's daughter here, you raped her,
you owe Shimon a thousand dollars." But really they're not saying you
owe Shimon a thousand dollars. Really even after גמר דין, gmar din,
they're saying you owe Rachel a thousand dollars and Shimon is going
to collect even after גמר דין, gmar din, says Rabbi Shimon. So
therefore as long as if the father dies before he's collected, even
after גמר דין, gmar din, the daughter's still going to pocket it
because the money always goes to the father through the daughter even
after גמר דין. gmar din. Do you have a פסוק? pasuk? No,
neither of them have a פסוק. pasuk. One minute, let's just read
the Mishnah top of מב עמוד א. Mem-bet amud aleph. מעשה ידיה
ומציאתה אף על פי שלא גבתה מת האב הרי הן של אחין.
Ma'aseh yadeha u'metzi'ata af al
pi shelo gavta met ha'av harei hen shel achin. However, this is
different even according to Rabbi Shimon. This case about collection for personal
injury is different from her earnings. Money that she earns, she I
don't know, she goes out and she weaves a garment or she
goes out and she gets a job, or she finds an object,
in that case even let's take the case of a job, it's
an easier example. So she's waiting to get her monthly salary and
then the father dies. It doesn't matter. Once that money was earned,
even before it's collected, then it really is automatically the father's money,
and if he dies, then it passes down הרי הן של אחין
Harei hen shel achin to the brothers. So that's interesting. Right? He's
not saying that every time the father collects on behalf of his
daughter, right? In most cases, right? As soon as the debt is
incurred, it becomes directly a debt to the father. Whereas for some
reason in the case of קנס, knas, according to Rabbi Shimon, even
after בית דין beis din has ruled, it still only gets paid
through the daughter, and if the father dies before it's been paid,
the daughter still collects. We'll see about why in the גמרא. Gemara.
How old is the girl in Rabbi Shimon's case?
Also 12 and a half, you know, under 12 and a half,
נערה קטנה, na'ara ktana, yes. נערה קטנה. na'ara ktana. Right? Once she's
a בוגרת, bogeret, it could be the same as the father dying.
Right? The father dying is assumed to be the same הלכה halacha
as her becoming a בוגרת. bogeret. Either way it's a scenario where
she becomes
emancipated, right? Before the end of the court case or before the
money's been collected.
But you're saying, Shadi, that Rabbi Shimon's saying if it passes the
brothers, it's a fine. Is that a fine?
It's not the passing the brothers is a funny way of thinking
about it. The brothers is only an issue about once we've said
whether it's the father's or hers, who the father's are collecting because
of an heir. He says that if it's a fine, it always
goes through her and therefore if the father has died when it
comes time to collect, even after the court has ruled, it's still
going to go through her, and therefore she's going to collect. Brothers
don't have the rights to her the same way the father does.
So
when the father's alive essentially she gets paid and then it transfers
to the father. Once the father is dead she gets paid and
it stops with her.
But in the case before that he's disagreeing with. Yeah. If he
passes away it goes first to the brothers and then.
No, according to the חכמים, Chachamim, the reason they say it goes
to the brothers is because logically what the חכמים Chachamim are saying
is that after גמר דין, gmar din, it's a debt directly to
the father. Okay? So there was a גמר דין, gmar din, it
became a debt directly to. to the father. The father died, so
the brothers inherit from the father. He's cut out. Okay? So whereas
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no even after גמר דין Gmar Din
it only gets to the father through her. So therefore even if
the father has died and she hasn't collected yet and the money
hasn't been paid yet, so it goes to- it would normally have
gone to her and then transferred immediately to the father. Right? It
would have been like call forwarding. Think of it like a type
of a call forwarding, okay? But there wasn't the call forwarding so
it stopped at her. Okay. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Headphone? Okay.
מאי Mai top of מב עמוד א. Mem-Bet Amud Aleph. מאי קמשמע
לן. Mai Kamashmalan. No talking guys, we're behind. מאי קמשמע לן. Mai
Kamashmalan. What is our משנה Mishnah teaching us? Now of course a
משנה Mishnah should be teaching us a lot but let's see what
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. Well, not not the whole
thing about who dies when and when and whatever, okay? תנינא, Tenina,
we already taught in an earlier משנה. Mishnah. המפתה נותן שלשה דברים
והאונס ארבעה. Hamfateh Notein Shlosha Devarim Ve'ones Arba.
So the first part of the משנה Mishnah we already knew, that
the seducer pays three payments and the rapist four. So the גמרא
Gemara says, המפתה נותן בושת ופגם וקנס. Hamfateh Notein Boshet Upegam Ukna's.
The seducer pays the בושת Boshet embarrassment, פגם Pegam injury, and the
קנס Knas fine. מוסיף עליו אונס שנותן את הצער Motif Alav Ones
She'notein Et Hatza'ar and the rapist adds to it that he gives
the צער Tza'ar pain suffering. לאביה. La'aviya. No. So the גמרא Gemara
says לאביה איצטריכא ליה. Laviya Itzrichleh. No, no, the חידוש Chidush here
was that it all goes to the father. The
גמרא Gemara says לאביה נמי פשיטא. Laviya Nami Peshita. That's also פשיטא
Peshita obvious. מדקיהיב מפתה. Mideka Yaiv Mefateh.
The fact that the seducer still has to pay even though she
did it all consensually. So that shows that it's the father who's
being paid. Because right, if it was
דאילו לעצמה De'ilu Atzmah because if the payment goes to
her, אמאי יהיב מפתה? Amai Yaiv Mefateh? Why did the- why-
why would the seducer pay? מדעתה עבד. Mi'da'atah Avad. He did it
based on her own acquiescence. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says fine. אמרה דבי דין איצטריכא ליה. Amra
De'bi Din Itzrichleh. פלוגתא דרבי
שמעון ורבנן. Pelugta De'Rabbi Shimon Ve'Rabbanan. So, so no,
so the whole חידוש Chidush here is what happens after the court
case, right? Has the father died before after the court case? Has
she become a בוגרת Bogeret before after the court case? The debate
of the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that's what this
is all about. That's the- the other stuff was just a lead-
lead into that. Okay fine. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay fine. Just one sec. Hold on one sec. I just want
to think about something one second. Yeah fine.
Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן. Tnan. תנן התם Tnan
Hatam we taught over there. אנסת ופתית את בתי. Onas Ufiti Et
Biti. This guy says you raped or seduced my daughter. Now this
is a משנה Mishnah in שבועות. Shevuot. Now in שבועות Shevuot the
following there's a הלכה Halacha about a קרבן Korban when you are
of- of כפירת ממון. Kfirat Mamon. If a person takes a vow
that somebody- that somebody says you know this is at the- this
is actually just weeks coming up פרשה. Parsha. Someone says וכחש בעמיתו
בפקדון או בתשומת יד או בגזל או עשק את עמיתו. Ve'kichesh Ba'amito
Bifkadon O Vishimut Yad O Vegazel O Ashak Et Amito. Right.
So basically somebody says where's that money that I- put gave you
for safe keeping? And the person takes- and says I don't know
what you're talking about. He says swear to me. So he takes
an oath and he's lying so he's using G-d's name and using
an oath as a way of- to steal. So besides the sin
of stealing it's also involving G-d in that process and therefore the
punishment is that he pays the principal plus a חומש Chamesh fifth
and he brings a special קרבן. Korban. Okay. So now in order
to do all of that it has to be a time- it
has to be a circumstance in which taking the oath is- is
denying something that were I to admit it I would have to
pay. And then here's another place where it matters whether something is
קנס Knas or ממון. Mamon. Because if something is ממון Mamon then
that's a type of an oath I'm חייב Chayav for because were
I to admit it I'd have to pay. Whereas if it's קנס,
Knas, if you tell me you stole from me and therefore you-
you pay let's say the principal I'm here to collect the כפל
Kefel but double payment and you say no no I've already paid
that up I don't know what you're talking about then I'm actually
not חייב Chayav for taking a false oath because even if I
were to admit that I owe you the כפל Kefel that admission
doesn't obligate me. Right? That's the principle again that מודה בקנס פטור.
Modeh Bi'knas Patur.
Right exactly. There you go. Okay so now here's the debate. So
here's the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay. אנסת ופתית את בתי. Onasta Ufiti Et Biti. This guy says
you raped or seduced my daughter. והוא אומר לא אנסתי ולא פתיתי
Vehu Omer Lo Onasti Velo Fititi I did not do it you're
making it up. משביעך אני Mashbi'acha Ani swear to me. ואמר אמן
Ve'amar Amen yes and he said אמן Amen he accepted the שבועה.
Shvua. ואחר הודה Ve'achar Hodeh and then he admitted that he had
raped or seduced the daughter. Okay. So is he being demanded ממון
Mamon or קנס Knas here? So חייב. Chayav. So he has to
pay. רבי שמעון פוטר. Rabbi Shimon Poter. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts.
שאינו משלם קנס על פי עצמו She'eino Meshalem Knas Al Pi Atzmo
because you would not pay even were you to admit that the
guy were to admit that he raped or seduced he would not
pay קנס. Knas. So therefore he does not pay by- by denying
since there would be no payment by admitting. So the גמרא Gemara
says אמרו לו Amru Lo they said to him אף על פי
שאינו משלם קנס על פי עצמו. Af Al Pi She'eino Meshalem Knas
Al Pi Atzmo. It's true for the קנס Knas you're not going
to have to pay by your own admission but משלם בושת ופגם
על פי עצמו, Meshalem Boshes u-Pegam al pi atzmo, but you would
pay for the embarrassment and the injury.
So now that line is part of this משנה.
Mishnah. Yes, that is part of this משנה. Mishnah. So it becomes
a very almost an inconsequential not really so much of a consequential
debate, cause they don't really seem as the גמרא Gemara is going
to be saying later on to be debating any of the legal
points. They both agree that you're not חייב Chayav for making a
false oath about a קנס, Knas, you're only חייב Chayav for making
a false oath about ממון. Mamon. The only question is that when
somebody says, "you raped my daughter," is he implicitly demanding the payment
for the קנס Knas and therefore a denial would not obligate the
person, or is he implicitly demanding the payment for the בושת ופגם
Boshes u-Pegam and therefore a denial would obligate the person? And why
don't I don't know why we don't say he's implicitly demanding both?
So the guy is at least חייב Chayav for the שבועה Shvuah
for the half of it that relates to the בושת ופגם? Boshes
u-Pegam? Anyway, that's their debate. When the guy says—everybody agrees you don't
pay for קנס, Knas, you do pay for ממון, Mamon, and similarly
there's no קרבן Korban for קנס, Knas, there's only a קרבן Korban
for ממון, Mamon, and the question is: which one is he really
demanding? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
That's the ברייתא. Braisa. So now the גמרא Gemara says the following,
and notice by the way it's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
So we're going—is anyone disagreeing?
But nobody in principle is disagreeing, which tells us—ah, so the גמרא
Gemara now is going to hone in on רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
even though there's no real reason to say there's a principal debate
between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן. Rabbanan. So let's take
a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. בעי מיניה אביי מרבה,
Ba'ei minei Abaye me-Rabbah, אביי Abaye asked רבה Rabbah the following question.
האומר לחבירו, Ha-omer le-chavero, somebody says to his fellow, אנסת ופיתית את
בתי, Anasta u-fitita es biti, you raped or seduced my daughter, ועמדתנו
בדין, Ve-amadtinu ba-din,
and not only did you do that act, we actually brought the
case to court, ונתחייבת לי ממון, Ve-nischayavta li mamon, and the court
ruled that you owed me the money. Okay? והוא אומר לא אנסתי
ולא פיתיתי ולא עמדתני בדין, Ve-hu omer lo anasti ve-lo fitisi ve-lo
amadtani ba-din, "No, it's all a lie, I never did it and
I never certainly was taken to court," ולא נתחייבתי לך ממון ונשבע
והודה, Ve-lo nischayavti lecha mamon ve-nishba ve-hodeh, and he never was obligated,
and he swore and then he admitted that he had lied. So
לרבי שמעון מה? Le-Rabbi Shimon mah? What's the story according to רבי
שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? All right, exactly. כיון דעמד בדין ממון הוי? Keivan
de-amad ba-din mamon havei?
Do we say once there was a court case, then the קנס
Knas converts to a case of ממון? Mamon? Okay? When we say
if I admit to a קנס, Knas, right, I don't get—I'm not
obligated, right? So let's say I say for example: "My ox gored
your slave." Okay? I'm not obligated because I'm admitting to a קנס.
Knas. And as we said, a קנס Knas is something that needs
to be imposed by בית דין. Beis Din. It won't—I won't be
able to obligate myself to it based on my own admission. But
let's say I say "My ox gored your slave and בית דין
Beis Din obligated me to pay." Am I now admitting to a
קנס? Knas? Or am I now admitting to ממון? Mamon? Right? I'm
actually saying that the fine had already been imposed by בית דין.
Beis Din.
It's still a קנס. Knas.
Okay, it's—it starts in a קנס, Knas, but now I'm admitting to
a debt that is imposed by בית דין, Beis Din, right? Part
of the reason my admission can't obligate me is because there's no
debt without בית דין Beis Din imposing it. Now I'm admitting to
the fact that בית דין Beis Din had imposed the debt. So
I'm admitting to a debt imposed by בית דין. Beis Din. Who
cares what it originated in? Does the חיוב Chiyuv of בית דין
Beis Din convert a קנס Knas to ממון? Mamon? That's generally the
assumption, that if I admit that I was obligated in a court,
I can obligate myself because then I don't need בית דין Beis
Din to impose it based on my own admission, it's already been
imposed, and I'm just admitting to a debt that's been imposed by
בית דין. Beis Din. So therefore that's the גמרא's Gemara question: is
that true? If what is being demanded and denied, claimed and denied,
is not the קנס Knas itself, but the קנס Knas imposed by
בית דין, Beis Din, would that already be considered ממון Mamon and
therefore you would be חייב Chayav a קרבן שבועה Korban Shvuah since
you—and
the related question is: would you be חייב Chayav based on just
admitting to that type of a debt?
As opposed to what?
As opposed to saying it still has the aspect, it still has
the character of קנס. Knas.
No, maybe because I'm on my own and pay you then. This
is already outside of בית דין. Beis Din. I'm going and saying,
"Well you know, I was already חייב Chayav in בית דין Beis
Din and here's your"—I
don't understand what you're talking about. קנס Knas is—קנס Knas starts with
something that I'm not obligated for based on my own admission. The
question is: does the nature of קנס Knas become converted to ממון
Mamon once בית דין Beis Din has created the obligation? And therefore
if I admit to an obligation of a קנס Knas imposed by
בית דין, Beis Din, am I not admitting to ממון? Mamon?
No, but maybe by the time—by the time I already come to
pay you, if it's not done in the בית דין Beis Din
at that same day, I'm already coming to
pay you after בית דין.
Beis Din. What?
What? I come to you and I say, "Michael, your ox gored
my slave," and you say—and I want to bring you to court,
and I want to bring—and I want to sort of get you
to pay. I don't understand what you're asking. At that stage, it's
only a קנס Knas and your own admission won't obligate you. If
I say a year ago this happened and בית דין Beis Din
imposed a debt, then I'm saying you owe me the money. I
don't need to bring you to בית דין Beis Din to prove
that your ox gored my slave, we did that a year ago.
Right, right. No, I'm saying, but—anytime by the time, like, you know,
I come around and I pay you, like, you know, if I—your
daughter, whatever it is.
Fine. Yes, exactly. At that time, it is ממון. Mamon. Correct. Fine.
Okay. Anyway, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
Okay, so לרבי שמעון מה? Le-Rabbi Shimon mah? What would we say?
The תוספות Tosafot says why you're only asking according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon is not clear, because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the
רבנן Rabbanan don't disagree in principle, but okay. כיון דעמד בדין ממון
הוי? Keivan de-amad ba-din mamon havei? Once there was a court case
it now actually exists as ממון mamon *mammon* and since we're debating
whether or not the court case existed you know in the past
what we're really debating is a ממון mamon *mammon* obligation and therefore
I would bring a קרבן שבועה Korban Shavuah *korban shvuah* and מחייב
ליה *mechayev lei* קרבן שבועה Korban Shavuah *korban shvuah* and I would
bring a קרבן שבועה Korban Shavuah? *korban shvuah* similarly it's a similar
question תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* explicitly even has this in the גרסא *girsa*
of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that if you're telling that I would
obligate myself based on my own admission and therefore there would be
a קרבן שבועה Korban Shavuah? *korban shvuah* because we're debating whether or
not the court has already found me guilty in the past או
דילמא *odilma* or do we say אף על גב דעמד בדין *af
al gav de'amad bedin* even though there's already been a court case
קנס knas. *knass* הוה *havah* it still retains its identity as a
קנס knas. *knass* since it started by קנס knas. *knass* it retains
its identity and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* by the way there's a debate
רש''י Rashi *Rashi* תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* here but I'll just say in
תוספות *Tosafot* says that therefore even were I to admit it even
were I to come and say I admit that last year you
I was found guilty in a בית דין *beis din* for my
ox goring your slave I don't have to pay you because it's
something that starts as קנס knas *knass* it always retains the character
of קנס knas, *knass* and I can never be obligated based on
my own admission and the same way I won't be obligated based
on my own admission I won't be obligated if I take a
שבועה *shvuah* okay so here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is asking a
core question about when קנס knas *knass* changes its identity to ממון
mamon *mammon* is it after the court case and then once which
is logical because now it just exists as a fine imposed by
court who cares what the past history of it is right I
mean if a court went ahead and found that I owed somebody
a thousand dollars or whatever now it's just a debt the past
history is irrelevant okay or do we say it still retains its
identity as קנס knas, *knass* and the נפקא מינא *nafka mina* is
when I admit to it do I have to pay and similarly
therefore when I deny it is there going to be a קרבן
שבועה Korban Shavuah, *korban shvuah* that's the question
so that's what אביי Abaye, *Abbaye* asked רבא Rava *Rava* אמר ליה
amar leh, *amar lei* רבא Rava *Rava* said back to him ממונא
הוא *mammona hu* מחייב ליה *mechayev lei* קרבן שבועה korban shevua, *korban
shvuah* it is ממון mamon? *mammon* at that stage and therefore if
you admit to it you're חייב chayav? *chayav* and if you deny
it you're going to bring a קרבן korban *korban* okay איתיבי eiseivei...
*eisvei* now let me ask on this רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon
omer, *Rebbe Shimon omer* we have a ברייתא Baraisa *braita* about this
קרבן שבועה korban shevua, *korban shvuah* רבי שמעון אומר Rebbi Shimon Omer,
יכול האומר לחבירו *Rebbe Shimon omer yakhol ha'omer lechavero* I would think
if somebody said to his friend אנסת ופתית את בתי *anasta upetita
et biti* that you have raped or seduced my daughter והוא אומר
לא אנסתי ולא פתיתי *ve'hu omer lo anasti velo pititi* I did
not never happened or he says הימי שורך את עבדי *hemi shorkha
et avdi* your ox gored my slave killed my slave thank you
והוא אומר לא הימי *ve'hu omer lo hemi* it did not happen
או שאמר לו עבדו *o she'amar lo avdo*
or his slave said to him הפלת את שיני *hippalta et shini*
you knocked out my tooth right and then the slave goes free
and that's interestingly considered to be a type of a קנס knass.
*knass* I don't know because maybe because it's disproportionate to the cost
of the tooth right so therefore that's considered to be a type
of a קנס knass *knass* וסימית את עיני *vesimata et eini* or
you blinded my eye והוא אומר לא הפלתי ולא סימיתי *ve'hu omer
lo hippalti velo simati* I did not do it okay so therefore
he's being demanded a קנס knass *knass* and he denies it ונשבע
והודה *venishba vehoda* and he swore falsely and then he admitted יכול
יהא חייב chayav, *yakhol yehei chayav* maybe you'd be obligated right the
interesting thing by the way is that a slave is bringing his
master to court and that's considered totally acceptable right the only question
here is whether it's a קנס knass *knass* or not maybe you'd
be חייב chayav *chayav* this קרבן korban. *korban* תלמוד לומר וכחש בעמיתו
V'chichesh b'amisso בפקדון או בתשומת יד או בגזל bagezel או עשק את
עמיתו *talmud lomar vekichesh ba'amito bepikadon o biteshumat yad o vegazel o
ashaq et amito* you deny your friend regarding a פקדון *pikadon* not
surety what's a פקדון *pikadon* a collateral no collateral פקדון *pikadon* is
just an object for safekeeping anyway or anyway you know or
some type of other type of abuse or stealing etc או מצא
אבידה avedah וכחש v'chichesh... בה *o matza aveida vekichesh bah* or you
found lost object and you denied that you had his lost object
in your house ונשבע על שקר *venishba al sheker* and you swear
falsely swore falsely then you bring this קרבן korban. *korban* מה אלו
מיוחדים שהן ממון mamon *mah elu meyuchadim shehen mammon* those things are
all monetary obligations אף כל שהן ממון mamon *af kol shehen mammon*
so similarly you'd only be חייב chayav *chayav* by something that's a
monetary obligation יצאו אלו שהן קנס knass, *yatze'u elu shehen knass* you're
not חייב chayav *chayav* when you swear falsely on something which is
only a קנס knass, *knass* okay that's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rebbe
Shimon* now what does that prove our question was what's the story
after גמר דין gmar din *gmar din* so that doesn't isn't clear
whether it's before or after גמר דין gmar din, *gmar din* so
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now comes to argue מאי לאו
בשעמד בדין *mai lav besha'amad bedin* are we not talking about since
we use the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* to prove it right here's like
a way of understanding it if really you would not be obligated
when you admitted to it you would not really need a פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* if you would concede you would not be obligated how
could you be found liable for lying and denying since you wouldn't
even be obligated if you conceded so maybe the assumption is since
we're using a פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* to prove it maybe the point
that we're proving is that even if it originated as קנס knass
*knass* even if it's after גמר דין *gmar din* it's still going
to be something you're going to be exempt of מאי לאו *mai
lav* are we not talking about בשעמד בדין *besha'amad bedin* that even
after even if what we're debating is an obligation based on something
in the past that there already was a court case about that
even there you'll be exempt because it started as a קנס knass
*knass* is that not the case
it'll always remain a קנס knass
*knass* it'll always retain its identity for a קנס knass. *knass* אמר
ליה לא בשלא עמד בדין amad bedin. *amar lei lo beshelo amad
bedin* no we're talking about before עמד בדין amad bedin. *amad bedin*
it's a straightforward קנס knass *knass* and that's why you're exempt but
maybe it would change its identity afterwards. The גמרא says one minute.
דהא מדרישא בשעמד בדין סיפא נמי בשעמד בדין. deha midreisha beshe'amad bedin
seifa nami beshe'amad bedin. One minute, the beginning of that ברייתא Baraisa
is talking about that there was a court case, so the end
of it must also be that there's a court case. What was
the beginning?
דתני רישא. detani reisha. We taught in the beginning of the ברייתא
Baraisa. and this is now a position of the חכמים, Chachamim, not
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אין לי אלא דברים שמשלמים עליהם את הקרן.
ein li ela devarim shemeshalmim aleihem et hakeren.
I only know that you bring a קרבן שבועה korban shevua things
that you pay the principal. תשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה ואונס ומפתה
ומוציא שם רע מנין? tashlumei kefel vetashlumei arba'ah vachamishah ve'ones umefateh umotsi
shem ra minayin? How do I know that you even do a
קרבן שבועה korban shevua on things like payment of double and four
and five and various cases of burglary or cases of seduction and
rape and libel, all these are קנס. knass. How do I know
even there you bring a קרבן שבועה? korban shevua תלמוד לומר ומעלה
מעל ריבה. talmud lomar uma'alah ma'al riba.
And you did a trespass, so that double language is to tell
me even in cases of קנס. knass So basically what's confusing about
this is that we've got the רישא reisha and the סיפא, seifa,
and the רישא reisha is the רבנן Rabbanan and the סיפא seifa
is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon So the רישא reisha says how do
I know that אונס ומפתה, ones umefateh, I mean it has other
cases as well but we'll just focus on אונס ומפתה. ones umefateh.
How do you know that you bring a קרבן שבועה? korban shevua.
קרבן שבועה, korban shevua how do we know you're חייב? chayav Because
it says ומעלה מעל. uma'alah ma'al. And then it says that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says,
אונס ומפתה, ones umefateh, you're going to be פטור patur because it
says וכחש וכחש, vechichesh vechichesh,
שם רע shem ra or בגזל whatever,
אבידה etc. blah blah blah, which is basically ממון mamon. and not
קנס. knass So here you have the ברייתא. First it says אונס
ומפתה ones umefateh you're חייב, chayav and then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says אונס ומפתה ones umefateh you're פטור. patur. Okay, so this is
understood to be the חכמים, Chachamim, although they weren't said. So it's
a debate whether you're חייב chayav or not by אונס ומפתה. ones
umefateh. So the גמרא says there is no way the חכמים Chachamim
would say that you're going to be חייב chayav if it was
not עמד בדין. amad bedin, It is impossible to conceive
that you could be חייב chayav, for denying something that were you
to have admitted it you'd also be exempt. So if the חכמים
Chachamim are saying you're חייב chayav for אונס ומפתה, ones umefateh, they
must be talking about עמד בדין. amad bedin.
But קנס knass requires עמד בדין, amad bedin. no?
Well yeah, but you could admit to the act before the עמד
בדין. amad bedin. Okay, but if you're going to be חייב chayav
for denying a case of קנס, knass it would only be some
type of a קנס knass that had you admitted to it you
would have been חייב chayav, for. Okay, so therefore if the חכמים
Chachamim say you're חייב chayav. for denying a קנס, knas it must
have been a case of עמד בדין. amad bedin. And therefore when
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you're פטור, patur, it's also got to
be a case of עמד בדין. amad bedin. So you see רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts you even in a case of
עמד בדין. amad bedin. Okay, so that's a pretty good proof that
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon, approach applies even after עמד בדין. amad bedin
So אמר ליה, so רבא Rava said back to אביי, Abaye יכילנא
לשנויי לך, yachilna leshunaye lach, I could answer you, רישא בשעמד בדין
וסיפא בשלא עמד בדין וכולה רבי שמעון היא. reisha beshe'amad bedin veseifa
beshelo amad bedin vechulah Rabbi Shimon hi. I could say to you
that actually no, here where it says you're חייב, chayav here where
it says you're חייב chayav, is because it was עמד בדין. amad
bedin. Here where it says you're פטור patur is when it was
לא עמד בדין. lo amad bedin. And there's really no debate of
חכמים Chachamim and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon. actually it's all
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. is
saying אונס ומפתה ones umefateh you're חייב chayav if it was after
עמד בדין amad b'din. and it became ממון mamon. and therefore if
you admit you'd be חייב, chayav? so if you deny you're חייב.
chayav And however אונס ומפתה ones umefateh you're פטור patur if it
was before עמד בדין. amad b'din Okay, so I could say that
the חייב chayav is after and the פטור patur is before and
it's all רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon But he says, ושינויי דחיקא לא
משנינן לך, veshinnuye dechikah lo meshaninan lach, I'm not going to give
you a bad answer, דאם כן, de'im ken, because if I were
to claim that, אמרת לי, amarta li, you'd say back to me,
ליתני רישא רבי שמעון אומר, lisni reisha Rabbi Shimon omer, that רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon name should have appeared at the beginning, או ליתני
סיפא דרבי שמעון, o lisni seifa deRabbi Shimon, or it should appear
at the very end. The fact that here it says אונס ומפתה
ones umefateh you're חייב, chayav. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says אונס ומפתה
ones umefateh you're פטור. patur. It does not sound like it's all
Rabbi Shimon. It sounds like, right, it's a debate of the חכמים
chachamim and Rabbi Shimon. And you've done a good job proving that
the חכמים chachamim would not say חייב unless it was עמד בדין.
amad b'din So we see clearly that
Rabbi Shimon says
פטור patur even after עמד בדין amad b'din it retains its character
of קנס. knas ומודינא לך u'modinu lach but I will concede to
you לענין קרבן שבועה דרחמנא פטריה. l'inyan korban shevua d'Rachmana patrei. When
it comes to the case of the קרבן שבועה, korban shevua there
we have a special פסוק. pasuk There I agree. My argument would
be that according to Rabbi Shimon, after עמד בדין amad b'din it
becomes ממון mamon, in other areas. Okay, but when it comes to
the קרבן שבועה, korban shevua, there you're right. There Rabbi Shimon says
that remains the identity of a קנס knas. and you remain off
the hook. Okay, because the Torah exempted it מכחש. me-V'chichesh. The פסוק
pasuk of וכחש בעמיתו etc. is to tell you that by קרבן
שבועה korban shevua. if it started as קנס knas. you're off the
hook. So now again, this is confusing. To remind you what we've
said.
The question אביי asked רבא Rava is, after עמד בדין amad b'din...
according to Rabbi Shimon, does קנס knas. convert to ממון? mamon And
his answer was yes. Actually he said yes for קרבן שבועה korban
shevua it does. But now he's taking back the קרבן שבועה korban
shevua. part of the claim. Because now we've proven that for Rabbi
Shimon even after עמד בדין amad b'din it retains its character for
קנס, knas you're still off the hook for קרבן שבועה. korban shvuah,
So he says fine. For Rabbi Shimon when it comes to קרבן
שבועה korban shvuah there's a special פסוק, even after עמד בדין... amad
b'din? וכחש... even after עמד בדין amad b'din it still has its
character of קנס, knas. you're still off the hook. But what I
meant to say was that it will convert to ממון mamon. for
all other purposes. But for קרבן שבועה korban shvuah you'll be off
the hook according to Rabbi Shimon.
קנס knas becomes ממון mamon. but the קרבן korban. remains as a
קנס knas. and he's פטור? patur?
Well, that's a funny way of saying it. In the laws of
קרבן שבועה, korban shvuah, if it... there's a special requirement that it
starts its life as ממון. mamon? Something that started its life as
קנס knas is technically exempt from the קרבן שבועה. korban shvuah, But
in other areas of הלכה, halacha, in general, if I had... what
is the identity of this thing now that it's עמד בדין? amad
b'din Its identity is ממון. mamon But even though right now it's
ממון, mamon, you're off the hook for קרבן שבועה korban shvuah because
it started its life as קנס. knas.
קנס knas to ממון mamon. after עמד בדין amad b'din already?
Well, first of all, if he... if you admit to it, are
you חייב? Right? So there's a whole מחלוקת machlokes רש"י תוספות Rashi
Tosfos at this stage what we think the story would be according
to Rabbi Shimon if you would admit to it. But, you know,
then the other issue about the father dying and it transferring to
the sons and all those issues, okay. So basically he's saying look,
my claim still is that according to Rabbi Shimon after עמד בדין
amad b'din it converts to ממון. mamon, You have proved to me
that according to Rabbi Shimon you're off the hook for... for קרבן.
Fine. That's a special הלכה halacha in קרבן. It has to start
its life not as a קנס. knas. If it started its life
as קנס you're off the hook. That's for the קרבן. But basically,
in all other הלכות, halachos, this thing is considered to be ממון.
mamon Okay, so now the גמרא says like this:
וכי קאמינא ממון v'chi kamina mamon so for what הלכה halacha do
I say it's
ממון? mamon להורישו לבניו, l'horisho l'banav, to bequeath it to your children.
Now we would say the easiest thing to say ממון mamon is
if you admit it, are you חייב or not. There there's a
debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות what the הלכה halacha would be
there. But his case of להורישו לבניו l'horisho l'banav is going to
turn us to our משנה, Mishna, which means that in... it's a
general point, like if somebody dies, right, you know, people owe this
guy a million dollars, those debts transfer to the sons, right? Because
it's part of the estate. But a קנס is not that way,
because a קנס is not yet a debt. So a קנס does
not transfer with the estate, doesn't get bequeathed to the children, if
it only existed as a קנס at the time that the guy
died. So here's the question: after עמד בדין amad bedin the guy
died, then he would say then Rabbi Shimon would say it's ממון,
mamon it would be bequeathed to the children. And also רש"י Rashi
would say also by the way the more simpler example, also if
you admitted to the debt you'd be חייב because it's already ממון.
mamon. So after עמד בדין amad bedin it would be considered ממון,
mamon. it would transfer to the children if the guy died, it
would... if you admitted you'd be חייב. It's only an exemption from
the laws of the קרבן שבועה. korban shvuah. Okay, so that's what
now רבא is claiming. So now the גמרא says like this: איתיבי...
eiseivei... so we're not done with רבא yet, because now we're going
to show a contradiction to this, which is our משנה. Mishna. Now
we finally tie back into our משנה. Mishna. איתיבי... רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon אומר, אם לא הספיקה לגבות עד שמת האב, im lo hispika
ligbos ad shemes ha'av, the money wasn't collected that was owed to
this daughter before the father died. Now remember what we just said.
There was a גמר דין and then the father's going to die.
So we are now claiming that Rabbi Shimon admits that when it's
a גמר דין, it gets converted to ממון mamon. and it becomes
a debt to the father, and if the father dies, it gets
bequeathed to the estate, right? That's what we said, that it does
get converted to ממון mamon for Rabbi Shimon in the משנה. Mishna.
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says that no, that until the money's paid
out, it'll still go to the girl. It doesn't become a debt
to the father that gets bequeathed to the estate. Right? Okay. רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon אומר, אם לא הספיקה לגבות, im lo hispika ligbot,
if she didn't collect the money עד שמת אב ad she-meis av
until the father died, הרי הן של עצמה harei hen shel atzmah
she keeps it. So just the fact that there's עמד בדין amad
bedin. does not make it ממון mamon to the father and to
get bequeathed to the estate. ואי אמרת ממונא הוי להוריש לבניו, ve-i
amart mamona havei lehorish le-banav, if after עמד בדין amad bedin. it
becomes a monetary debt that he bequeaths to the children, so לעצמה
אמאי, le-atzmah amai, why does she keep it? דאחיהן בעו למהוי, d'achiyan
ba'u le-mehavi, it should go to the brothers, to the father's sons.
It's a ירושה. yerusha. So why does רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon disagree
with the משנה? mishna? So that seems to be that רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon, in general considers something to remain a קנס even after
עמד בדין. amad bedin. אמר רבה, Amar Rabba, so רבה Rabba says,
היי מילתא קשיא ביה לרבה ולרב יוסף עשרין ותרתין שנין. hai milsa
kashya beh le-Rabba u-le-Rav Yosef esrin v'sartin shanin.
רבה Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef were challenged by this issue
for 22 years. Now תוספות points out, why did you have to
worry about it? Why not just retract your statement? Right, all of
the evidence points to the idea that for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
it remains a קנס until the very end, even after עמד בדין.
amad bedin So why are you having such a hard time, "oh
I can't fit this into the משנה," mishna, just change your opinion!
Say look, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon? says it remains a קנס. So
תוספות says it's clear that they had a tradition that even according
to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, it got converted to ממון mamon. after
עמד בדין. amad bedin But now he's got a problem. In the
case of קרבן שבועה, Korban Shvua, it's clear that it's still a
קנס. It's clear that after עמד בדין amad bedin you're still off
the hook. In the case of להוריש לבניו lehorish lebanav in our
משנה, mishna, it's clear that even after עמד בדין amad bedin, it
does not go to the sons. It remains a קנס. So רבה
Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef couldn't figure out how to explain
their tradition that according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon it got converted
to ממון. mamon Because we see for קרבן שבועה it's considered a
קנס and we see for bequeathing to the kids it's not considered
ממון. mamon. So they couldn't understand it for 22 years. ולא איפרק
v'lo ifrik and it was not answered
עד דיתיב רב יוסף
ברישא ופרק
ad deyativ Rav
Yosef
be-reisha u-farak until רב יוסף Rav Yosef became the ראש ישיבה. Rosh
Yeshiva. Now רבה Rabba was the head of the ישיבה Yeshiva for
22 years. At that, you know, there's a whole debate who should
be the head of the ישיבה, Yeshiva, רבה Rabba or רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, because רבה Rabba was the bigger תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
but רב יוסף Rav Yosef was the bigger בקי. baki. So basically
רבה Rabba was the head of the ישיבה, Yeshiva, and then after
22 years he died, then רב יוסף Rav Yosef became the head
of the ישיבה. Yeshiva. So רש"י says a very beautiful thing, that
even though רב יוסף Rav Yosef was more of the בקי baki
and רבה Rabba was more of like the sharp analytical תלמיד חכם,
talmid chacham, דווקא davka in order to give status to רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, he was assisted מן השמים min hashamayim that he answered
a question that רבה Rabba couldn't answer. So at the end of
the 22 years he now became the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva and
he was able to figure out the answer. Okay. So עד דיתיב
רב יוסף ברישא ופרק, ad deyativ Rav Yosef be-reisha u-farak, רב יוסף
Rav Yosef became the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva and he answered it.
שאני התם דאמר
קרא, shani hatam de-amar kra, you know what? The case of אונס
ומפתה ones u'mefateh is also an exception to the rule because there's
a lot of exceptions. Because the פסוק says ונתן האיש השוכב עמה
לאבי הנערה חמישים כסף. v'nasan ha-ish ha-shochev imah l'avi ha-na'arah chamishim kasef.
He should give to the father 50 כסף. kesef. So it says
the money shall already be given. לא זכתה תורה לאב אלא משעת
נתינה. lo zachatah Torah l'av ela mishe'as nesina. The father doesn't have
any right to it except משעת נתינה mishe'as nesina from the time
of giving. Until it's given, it's always fundamentally owed to the daughter.
Okay, so you're right, you know what? In general it would be
ממון. mamon In this case though, it's still קנס. Or if you
want to say it in a different way, in this case it's
still being paid through the daughter and it's not direct to the
father. וכי
קאמר רבה ממונא הוי להוריש
לבניו,
v'chi ka-amar Rabba mamona havei
lehorish lebanav, and when did רבה, Rabba, עליו השלום alav hashalom who
has now passed away, when did he say it's ממון after עמד
בדין amad bedin according to רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon בשאר קנסות, bish'ar
knasot, in other fines. So now we have two exceptions. Even according
to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon קנס transfers to ממון when it's עמד
בדין, amad bedin except number one in a קרבן שבועה we got
a פסוק that says you're off the hook because it started as
קנס. And number two by אונס ומפתה ones u'mefateh even after עמד
בדין amad bedin it's still being paid through the daughter. So if
the father dies, the daughter's going to get it. It's not direct
ממון. What? Right.
Okay. So for something that's not אונס ומפתה ones u'mefateh and not
a קרבן שבועה, in other cases after עמד בדין amad bedin... it
gets converted. Let's just read one more line. אלא מעתה, ela me-ata,
if that's true, גבי עבד דכתיב כסף שלושים שקלים יתן לאדוניו, gabei
eved d'chsiv kesef shloshim shekalim yitein l'adonav, so it also says give
straight to the master. הכא נמי לא זכתה תורה לאדון אלא משעת
נתינה? hacha nami lo zachatah Torah l'adon ela mishe'as nesina? Maybe also
it's not considered his and it's not a monetary debt until the
money's actually paid out? יתן yitein לחוד lachud ונתן v'nasan לחוד. lachud.
There's a difference between יתן yitein
which means you'll still give it, even let's say after the guy
dies you'll give it to the sons, and ונתן v'nasan means it's
already been given. So in the case by the אונס ומפתה ones
u'mefateh it's only considered to be ממון once it's already been given.
Okay, so one more time what we're saying is: רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon basically if you really look at it, you look at רבי
שמעון in the משנה mishna and you look at רבי שמעון by
the קרבן שבועה, it seems like רבי שמעון says קנס always remains
a קנס. But comes along רבה Rabba with a tradition and says
no, after עמד בדין amad bedin. it gets converted to ממון. But
we have to now make exceptions. קרבן שבועה is an exception, there
it remains a קנס and therefore you're not going to give a
קרבן שבועה. אונס ומפתה ones u'mefateh is an exception, and even after
עמד בדין... amad bedin It remains not directly to the father but
it goes through the daughter, and if the father dies, the daughter's
going to get it even after עמד בדין. But for other areas,
not קרבן שבועה, not אונס ומפתה, Oness u'mefateh, there after עמד בדין
it's going to be considered a ממון and no longer a קנס.
All right.